The Ring of the Fisherman,
which bears the official papal seal...
...must be destroyed immediately
following the pope's death.
The papal apartment is then sealed
for nine days of mourning...
...a period known as sede vacante:
The time of the empty throne.
Over the last several days...
...Catholic leaders from every corner
of the world...
...have flocked to Rome,
shocked by the sudden death...
...of this progressive
and beloved pope.
Today, in St. Peter's Square...
...the faithful pray
that there is among them...
...another leader
who can unite their Church...
...which has been so riven by change
and dissent in recent years.
As the body of the pontiff
passes by...
...we see prayers are being offered
by the preferiti...
...favorites among those
being considered...
...to succeed him
as the Vicar of Christ.
At the end of the mourning period,
the College of Cardinals...
...will lock itself behind the doors
of the Sistine Chapel for conclave...
...the process by which they
will choose a new leader...
...for the world's
one billion Catholics...
...who now find their Church
at a crossroads...
...its ancient traditions threatened
by a modern world.
Attention, control group going online
for LHC beam event.
We are powering up.
Attention, Category One personnel:
Interlock areas are now restricted.
ATLAS underground
is now in restricted mode.
Protons are being loaded.
Powering on LHC magnets.
Ion source stage
in four, three, two....
We are powering up. Here we go.
Start the collision sequence.
Beam-on-beam stability is good.
Take your places, people.
ATLAS at CMS, check.
We have got 10 to the 13th protons
per bunch.
Let's hope the heavy ion guys
didn't mess up.
Beams at relativistic velocities.
Luminosity monitors operational.
Beamline has no restrictions.
Enable beam capture.
Accelerating the beam.
Stage one, line up.
Magnets to full field.
Load functions to magnets.
Last P is still too high.
Yeah, we got luminosity of 10 to 34.
Inject particle beams.
Filling the LHC.
Particles in transition.
Collisions are fixed and running.
LHC injecting protons, beam one.
Lock the feedback systems.
Particles at 99 percent
the speed of light.
Colliding stable beams.
Enact injection kicker.
We have a signal
on the luminosity monitors.
We have events.
Protons are moving.
That's a crate of beer on the way.
A swim might help your jet lag.
I beg your pardon?
You got bags under your eyes.
It's 5 in the morning.
And you're from the Vatican.
Crossed keys under the triregnum.
It's a papal symbol.
Claudio Vincenzi,
Corpo della Gendarmeria Vaticano.
Vatican police?
I was expecting another letter.
My request for access
to your archives.
Shouldn't you be in Rome?
A kind of busy time for you guys,
isn't it?
In fact, I was in New York,
detailed to the U.N.
I receive a phone call
in the middle of the night:
"Find Professor Robert Langdon.
A matter of great urgency."
They said to show you this.
The Illuminati? They disappeared
hundreds of years ago.
Did they? Look at that again.
It's an ambigram.
It's the same image
forward and backward.
Now, that's common for a symbol,
like a yin and yang or a swastika...
...but that's a word.
That Illuminati
ambigramatic symbol...
...has been considered a myth
for 400 years.
Supposedly, in the 16th century...
...some artist created it as a tribute
to Galileo's love of symmetry.
It was only gonna be revealed...
...when the Illuminati
had amassed enough power...
...to resurface and carry out
their final goal.
I wrote a book about it.
Which is why you're here.
The Art of the Illuminati
by Robert Langdon.
Part One.
Haven't been able to finish Part Two.
I'm not allowed access...
...to your archives.
It's remarkable. Singular.
Someone is trying
to make you believe...
...the Illuminati themselves
have returned to Rome.
Right after the death of a pope.
Four cardinals were kidnapped
from inside the Vatican...
...sometime between
3 and 5 a.m. this morning.
Shortly afterward...
...that document was sent
to the Office of the Swiss Guard...
...along with the threat the cardinals
will be publicly executed...
...one per hour, beginning at 8 p.m.
tonight in Rome.
-Conclave.
-Was to begin today.
We've postponed its start
for a few hours, a story of illness.
There are no suspicions yet.
What do you want from me?
These criminals
who sent this ambigram...
...meant it as a taunt, a provocation.
But Captain Olivetti think if you can
use it to learn their identity...
...perhaps we can stop
this abomination.
Why me?
Your expertise. Your erudition.
Your recent involvement
with certain Church, shall we say...
...mysteries.
I wasn't under the impression
that episode...
...had endeared me to the Vatican.
Oh, it didn't.
But it did make you--
What's the word?
--formidabile.
Formidable.
A Vatican jet is standing by
20 minutes from here.
Will you come with me?
Professore Langdon,
you've spent your life...
...searching for symbols like the one
you now hold in your hand.
How much longer are we
going to pretend...
...you have not already
decided to come?
If the Illuminati have returned
and are in Rome...
...we will hunt them down
and kill them.
The Illuminati
did not become violent...
...until the 17th century. Their name
means "the enlightened ones."
They were physicists
and mathematicians, astronomers.
They were concerned with
the Church's inaccurate teaching...
...and were dedicated
to scientific truth.
But the Vatican didn't like that.
So the Church began to--
How did you say it?
Oh, "hunt them down and kill them."
Drove them underground.
Into a secret society.
Excuse me.
Comandante Richter assures me
the guard...
...is doing everything humanly possible
to find the prefefiti.
A long way to say very little.
What if you were to begin
in their absence?
They are the four leading candidates.
If they're not present,
they're not eligible.
There will be no consensus without
them. Who are we to vote for?
It is as much a sin to offer flattery
as to accept it.
May I suggest you at least consider
the possibility.
No, no, no. There is no possibility.
I have been chosen Great Elector.
I am not eligible.
Camerlengo asks how long we can
postpone the opening prayer...
...without making another
announcement to the public.
Tell the camerlengo the cardinal-elect
will take every minute required...
...to perform the sacred trust.
No further announcements
are necessary.
He'll be concerned
about the public dimension.
-People will think--
-What we tell them to think.
-Professor Langdon.
-Yes.
Welcome to Vatican City.
Ernesto Olivetti, inspector general
of the Vatican police force.
-My pleasure.
-This way, please.
We'll meet in the headquarters
of the Swiss Guard.
I thought you were Swiss Guard.
No, la Gendarmeria.
We are responsible for everything
inside the Vatican walls...
...with the exception
of the security of His Holiness...
-Yeah.
-...and the Apostolic Palace.
That is Swiss Guard.
The Roman carabinieri are here
as well in an advisory capacity.
So jurisdictionally, this is....
A goddamn nightmare.
Oh, yes, Pope Pius IX's
great castration.
-l beg your pardon?
-1857, Pope Pius IX...
...felt the male form
would inspire lust.
So he took a hammer and chisel...
...and unmanned hundreds
of these statues.
The plaster fig leaves
were added later.
Are you anti-Catholic,
Professor Langdon?
No. I'm anti-vandalism.
I urge you to guard your tone here.
The Swiss Guard is a calling,
not a profession...
...and it encourages
a certain zealotry.
Commander Richter,
the head of the Guard...
...is a deeply spiritual man...
...and he was close
to the late pope. Understood?
Look, I don't study symbols
because I consider them unimportant.
Ceremony, traditions,
it's how we mark our lives.
I just-- I just hope I can help.
So do l.
You were my idea.
Wait here. Please.
Commander?
Commander Richter?
Professor Langdon is here.
Well, we have bigger problems
than that now.
Dr. Vetra?
I'm Commander Richter, comandante
principale of the Swiss Guard.
Thank you for coming.
Hello.
-Professor Langdon.
-Yes.
What a relief,
the symbologist is here.
This way, please, Miss Vetra.
The situation has changed.
We received another threat
from the kidnapper.
The canister was stolen from our lab
around noon yesterday.
The intruder killed my research
partner, Silvano Bentivoglio...
...and mutilated him
in order to bypass security.
We use retinal scanners.
They cut out his eye.
Is that your stolen canister,
Miss Vetra?
Where is that camera, Number 86?
It's wireless. It too was stolen.
It could be anywhere
inside the Vatican.
That canister contains
an extremely combustible substance.
We need to locate it immediately
or evacuate Vatican City.
I'm quite familiar
with incendiaries, Miss Vetra.
I've never heard of antimatter
being used as such.
Well, it's never been generated
in significant quantities before.
It's a way of studying the origins
of the universe...
...to try to isolate what some people
call "the God particle."
But there are implications
for energy research--
"The God particle"?
What we call it isn't important.
It's what gives all matter mass.
The thing without which
we could not exist.
You're talking about
the moment of creation.
Yes. In a way, I am.
The antimatter is suspended there...
...in an airtight nanocomposite shell
with electromagnets in each end.
If it were to fall out of suspension
and come in contact with matter...
...say, the bottom of the canister,
the two opposing forces...
...would annihilate one another
violently.
And what might cause it
to fall out of suspension?
The battery going dead.
-Which it will, just before midnight.
-What kind of annihilation?
-How violent?
-A cataclysmic event.
A blinding explosion equivalent
to about five kilotons.
Vatican City
will be consumed by light.
Those are the exact words
the kidnapper used.
We will destroy your four pillars.
We will brand your preferiti...
...and sacrifice them
on the altars of science...
...then bring your church down
upon you.
Vatican City
will be consumed by light.
A shining star at the end
of the Path of Illumination.
It's the ancient Illuminati threat.
Destruction of Vatican City
through light.
Four pillars,
there's your kidnapped cardinals.
You didn't tell me they
were the prefefiti, the favorites...
...to be named the next pope.
Play it again.
We will destroy your four pillars.
We will brand your preferiti--
Wait, stop it. Stop it.
"Brand" them.
That's another Illuminati legend.
This one says
that there are a set of five brands...
...each one an ambigram.
The first four are the fundamental
elements of science:
Earth, air, fire and water.
The fifth, it's a mystery.
Maybe it's this.
He said they'd be killed publicly.
Yes.
Revenge for la purga.
"La purga"?
Oh, jeez, you guys don't even read
your own history, do you?
1668, the Church kidnapped
four Illuminati scientists...
...and branded each one of them
on the chest...
...with the symbol of the cross...
...to purge them of their sins,
and they executed them.
Threw their bodies into the street
as a warning...
...to others to stop questioning
Church rulings on scientific matters.
They radicalized them.
The purga created a darker,
more violent Illuminati...
...one bent on retribution.
Look how they intend
to finally get it:
Using antimatter, technology,
to destroy the Church.
Science obliterates religion.
Is there any more?
--and sacrifice them
on the altars of science...
...then bring your church down
upon you.
Vatican City will be consumed
by light.
A shining star at the end
of the Path of Illumination.
"Path of Illumination."
I need access
to the Vatican archives.
Professor, I don't think
this is the appropriate--
Your petition has been denied
seven times.
No, no. This has nothing to do with
my work. The Path of Illumination...
...is a trail that leads
to the Church of the Illumination...
...the place where the Illuminati
would meet in secret.
If I can find the segno, the sign...
...that marks the beginning of that
path, the four churches along it...
...may be where he intends
to murder your cardinals.
One every hour at 8, 9, 10 and 11.
Then the device explodes
at midnight.
If we can figure out the first church
and get there before he does...
...maybe we can stop it.
But I can't find the start of the path...
...until I get into the archives.
Even if I wanted to help you...
...access to the archives
is only by written decree...
...by the curator
and the Board of Vatican Librarians.
Or by papal mandate.
Yes, but as you no doubt have heard,
the Holy Father is dead.
What about il camerlengo?
The camerlengo is just a priest here,
the former pope's chamberlain.
Doesn't the power of the Holy See rest
in him during tempe sede vacante?
Fellas, you called me.
His Holiness once told me a pope...
...was a man torn between
the real world and the divine.
It seems the real world
is upon us tonight.
I'm familiar with Illuminati lore
and the legend of the brandings.
La purga is a dark stain
on this Church's history.
I'm not surprised this ghost
has returned to haunt us.
Comandante, have you begun
the search for this explosive device?
Of course, but it could be anywhere.
My primary concern at the moment
is the safety of the cardinals.
The Sistine Chapel is a fortress.
As long as the cardinals
are in conclave, your concerns...
...are at a minimum.
Devote as many of your resources--
If you're about to suggest
a naked-eye search...
...of the entire Vatican City, I will tell
you we do not have the people.
Though I am not His Holiness,
when you are addressing me...
...you are addressing this office.
Do you understand?
Yes, Father.
Good.
You said the image on the screen
was illuminated by artificial light.
Might I suggest
methodically cutting power...
...to various sections of the city.
When the image goes dark,
you'll have a specific idea...
...of the camera's location.
Dr. Vetra, besides yourself
and your research partner...
...who else knew
about this antimatter project?
No one but the research team.
This project was strictly confidential.
But Silvano kept detailed journals.
If he told anyone else...
...about what we were doing,
he would have made a note.
Do you have these journals?
I can have them flown here
from Geneva in an hour.
Please.
Professor Langdon.
Mr. Langdon, you are correct that I
may grant you access to the archives.
Thank you, Padre.
I said that you were correct
that I may, not that I will.
Christianity's most sacred codices
are in that archive.
Given your recent entanglement
with the Church...
...there is a question I'd like
to ask you first...
...in the office of His Holiness.
Do you believe in God, sir?
Father, I simply believe
that religion--
I did not ask if you believe
what man says about God.
I asked if you believe in God.
I'm an academic.
My mind tells me I will never...
...understand God.
And your heart?
Tells me I'm not meant to.
Faith is a gift...
...that I have yet to receive.
Be delicate with our treasures.
The archives are this way.
Professor Langdon.
If this path really leads
to the Church of Illumination...
...that may be where they've hidden
the antimatter.
"A shining star
at the end of the path."
Follow the path.
-We may find the canister.
-Can you deactivate the device?
I can change the batteries...
...as long as we have
more than five minutes.
That would give us another 24 hours
to get it safely back to CERN.
Robert Langdon.
Vittoria Vetra.
Are you really a symbologist,
or was he mocking you?
Well, both. You're a physicist?
Bio-entanglement physics.
Interconnectivity of life systems.
Okay.
Your project, it was geared
towards energy research?
Eventually, yes.
One speck of antimatter
could power an entire city for a month.
Or tonight, I guess, destroy one.
What are we looking for
in the archives?
A bound volume written by Galileo.
Galileo was Illuminati?
Yeah. And an obedient Catholic
who didn't think...
...that Church and science
were enemies...
...but a different language
telling the same story.
He wanted like minds
to find the Church of Illumination...
...but he couldn't exactly advertise its
location so he created a coded path.
Richter has started to turn off
the power of various grids.
It'll be back on in a minute.
Then some unknown Illuminati master
sculpted four statues.
Each one a tribute to one
of the fundamental elements...
...earth, air, fire, water...
...and placed the statues out in public
in churches throughout Rome.
Each statue held a clue
pointing to the next.
At the end of the path
was the Church of Illumination.
If you could find that,
you were one of them.
What makes you think he's going
to murder in the churches?
The Illuminati called
those four churches...
...by the special name,
L'Altare della scienza.
"Sacrifice them on the altars
of science," he said.
Exactly.
Oh, wow. Look at this.
Excuse me, signore.
Cardinal Strauss,
you've been informed of the situation?
Yeah.
My belief is we should proceed
with the sealing of conclave.
At this late hour?
That would be highly unorthodox.
And yet within Church law.
It's in my power. I am Great Elector.
The cruelest honor in Christendom.
I have no personal ambitions,
Patrick.
Only those I hold for my Church,
St. Peter's Church...
...which is under attack
at its most vulnerable moment.
And this is not a coincidence.
The Church will not fall in a day.
We must evacuate Vatican City.
Oh, that is exactly what they want.
Publicity and panic.
No, we must not give them oxygen
for the media fire.
But the people
in St. Peter's Square--
Care deeply about their Church,
as we do.
Their faith will sustain them.
Their faith will not protect them
from an explosion.
Well....
We are all bound for heaven
eventually, are we not?
Spoken like one who has enjoyed
the blessings of a long and full life.
Patrick...
...do not confuse the power
of the office you temporarily hold...
...with your true place
here in the Vatican.
You were a favorite
of His Holiness...
...but His Holiness
is with his father now.
Mea culpa.
Seal the doors.
Extra Omnes.
Hello. This way, please.
Oh, beautiful.
The chambers are hermetic vaults.
Oxygen is kept
at lowest possible levels.
It's a partial vacuum inside.
So extended stays
are not recommended.
So don't panic if you feel
lightheaded at first.
I'll be just outside the door.
Watching you, Mr. Langdon.
By the way,
it's normal to feel a little light-headed.
Yeah. Feels like I'm scuba diving
with the wrong mixture.
Take a second. We have time.
Actually, I take that back.
-ls that Mickey Mouse?
-Yeah. It's a long story.
Conclave will go on without us.
It must, now of all times.
May God forgive you
for what you've done.
Father, if God has issues...
...they won't be with what I've done.
They will be
with what I'm about to do.
It was confiscated
from the Netherlands...
...by the Vatican
just after Galileo died.
I've been petitioning to see it
for about 10 years...
...ever since I realized
what was in it.
What makes you so sure
the segno's there?
The number 503.
I kept seeing it over and over again
in Illuminati letters...
...scribbled in the margins,
sometimes just signed "503."
It's a numeric clue. But to what?
Five? Well, that's a meaningful
number to the Illuminati.
There's the pentagram, Pythagoras,
dozens of other examples in science.
But what about three?
Didn't make sense until I thought,
"What if it's Roman numerals?"
-DIII.
-D-three. Galileo's third text.
"Dialogo. Discorso. Diagramma."
Yeah.
Just a few days with this...
...and I could have
actually finished my book...
...and sold dozens of copies
at the Harvard bookstore.
"ll Diagramma Veritatis."
Diagram of Truth.
I know about Dialogo and Discorsi.
Galileo laid out his theories about
the Earth revolving around the sun.
Yeah, and said the Earth
was not the center of some universe...
...with heaven above, hell below,
as the Church had said.
So they forced him to recant in the
second book. But what was this one?
This is how he got the word out.
This is the truth, not what the Vatican
forced him to write.
Smuggled out of Rome, printed
in Holland on sedge papyrus, see?
That way any scientist caught with
a copy could just throw it in water...
...and Galileo's heresy
would dissolve, disappear.
And between that
and Vatican burnings...
...it's possible that
this is the only copy that remains.
And if I'm correct...
...the segno is hidden
on page number--
Five.
Yeah.
Do you need help with the Latin?
Sure.
Movement of the planets,
elliptical orbits, heliocentricity.
Sorry, I don't think there's anything
that could be interpreted as a--
Wait, wait, wait.
Do that again.
What is that?
Wait a minute, it's a watermark.
And there's a line of text.
Go back.
It's in English.
English? Why English?
English wasn't used in the Vatican.
It was too polluted.
It was free-thinking.
It was a language of radicals...
...like Shakespeare and Chaucer.
Here's another one. "The path of light
is laid, the sacred test--"
-Will you write this down as I dictate?
-Sorry, professor, no time.
Yeah, yeah, what the hell. Yeah.
Twenty minutes till 8.
-Where are we headed?
-Hold on, hold on.
I'll tell you in a minute.
Let me see that page again.
Where did you get that paper?
We borrowed it.
"From Santi's earthly tomb
with demon's hole."
Are you insane?
"'Cross Rome the mystic elements
unfold.
The path of light is laid,
the sacred test.
Let angels guide thee
on thy lofty quest."
You removed a document
from the Vatican Archives?
She did.
"From Santi's earthly tomb."
-The first marker is at Santi's tomb.
-Yeah.
-But who's Santi?
-Raphael.
-ll Raffaello, the sculptor?
-Yeah, Santi was his last name.
So the path starts
at Raphael's tomb.
Raphael's buried at the Pantheon.
-Isn't the Pantheon a church?
-Oldest Catholic church in Rome.
I just pulled a dozen of our best men
for this.
-You better be right.
-This is one of the busiest spots.
-He'd never get away with it.
-The poem implies--
"The poem"? Unbelievable.
I'm basing this operation...
...on an American's interpretation
of a 400-year-old poem.
The information we have
clearly refers to Raphael's tomb.
Raphael's tomb
is inside that building.
Because the Vatican destroyed all of
the pagan statues in the late-1800s...
...if this is the marker, whatever clues
were here to lead us are gone now.
The path is dead. So this is it,
your only chance.
Separate approaches.
No closer than two blocks
and no uniforms. Three minutes.
And I need a set of eyes inside.
Excuse me?
Weightlifters in matching suits and
earpieces? They're hardly disguised.
-Well, it's what I have.
-Fine, I'll go in.
You don't have communication.
You can't carry a walkie-talkie.
-Tourists have cell phones.
-No, no.
You can't send her in there alone.
All right, I won't.
Don't look so anxious.
We're supposed to be married.
Well, maybe we're not
getting along today.
Hold my hand.
-But don't crush it.
-Sorry. A nervous newlywed.
Oh, look. Look, honey, the oculus.
That could be the "demon's hole"
in the poem.
Why are the tombs at an angle?
They're facing east
to worship the rising sun.
But this is a Christian church.
New religions often adopt
the existing customs and holidays...
...to make conversion
less of a shock.
Like the 25th of December?
It's the pagan celebration
of the Unconquered Sun...
...and also makes a handy date
for the birth of Christ.
-Let's check the recesses.
-Okay.
I'll go to the right.
I'll meet you at 180 degrees.
Follow me, please.
Now, the Pantheon, which means
"Temple of All Gods"...
...was originally built as a temple
to all the gods of ancient Rome...
...in 27 B.C.
Although the design of the building
is usually credited...
...to Apollodorus of Damascus....
Robert!
Robert.
It's Raphael's tomb.
-But it's the wrong one.
-What are you talking about?
He was moved here in 1759, a century
after Diagramma was published.
Where was he originally buried?
Urbino, I think.
"Santi's earthly tomb."
What could it possibly be?
Damn it. Santi's tomb.
It must mean a chapel that he built.
He's not buried in it, he designed it.
The "demon's hole,"
it's not that oculus.
It's an undercroft. It's a crypt.
-Are there any questions?
-Yes.
Yes.
Did Raphael Santi ever design
a chapel with an ossuary annex...
...and an angel figure commissioned
by the Catholic Church?
I'm sorry, I can only think of one.
One is good.
-Wrong? What do you mean?
-It's the Chigi Chapel...
...in the church
of the Santa Maria del Popolo.
It was once called the Capella della
Terra, the Chapel of the Earth.
Earth, the first element. That's it.
-You were certain about the Pantheon.
-We have four minutes.
Back to the Vatican? You can't.
If you care at all
about your church, you'll listen.
My church?
My church comforts
the sick and dying.
My church feeds the hungry.
What does your church do,
Mr. Langdon?
That's right, you don't have one.
Take him if you want.
I'm done with him.
All right, this makes sense.
Look, right in front of the church.
An obelisk, a lofty pyramid.
Egyptian symbol
adopted by the Illuminati.
If he's going to kill him,
he'll do it here.
Eight o'clock.
Robert.
No, no, here. It's an annulus.
Which one is the Chigi Chapel?
It's in one of these apses.
Pyramids in a Catholic church.
This is it. This is the Chigi Chapel.
The demon's hole.
But it's askew.
Come here.
Hand me your flashlight.
What's that?
I call as my witness Christ the Lord...
...who will be my judge,
that my vote is given...
...to the one before God
I think should be elected.
I elect as the most high pontiff,
Dominic Scolamiero.
Edoardo Rossi.
They are voting for themselves
to prevent a majority.
They are waiting for the prefefiti
to be rescued.
Perhaps we should as well, yes?
Not until the smoke is white...
...will the College of Cardinals
have chosen a new Holy Father.
For now, the Vatican seat
of ultimate power remains vacant.
Get the body out of there,
and search the rest of the building.
-Chartrand!
-Sir?
Outside, a perimeter.
Secure but invisible.
No lights, no guns, nobody knows.
-Understand?
-Yes, sir.
I'm calling all off-duty.
No information.
Is it Raphael?
The chapel is Raphael.
But the sculptures are Bernini.
The unknown Illuminati master...
...Bernini?
He worked for the Church.
Almost exclusively.
But the Illuminati were infiltrators.
There wasn't a powerful organization
they didn't penetrate...
...including the Vatican
by hiding in plain sight.
Habakkuk and the Angel.
He's the prophet that predicted
the annihilation of the Earth.
"Let angels guide thee
on thy lofty quest."
This is the first marker.
The path is alive.
Southwest.
It was pointing southwest.
Earth, air, fire, water.
We're looking for a Bernini sculpture...
...having to do with air.
The second church is somewhere
southwest of here.
You're sure this time?
I need a map showing
all the churches of Rome.
I could use it now.
All right, the purple areas with these
black crosses represent the churches.
But nothing intersects the line
until it hits--
-Until it hits St. Peter's.
-Michelangelo designed St. Peter's...
-...not Bernini.
-Michelangelo designed the Basilica.
Bernini designed St. Peter's Square.
The second marker must be
a statue in St. Peter's Square.
It's 10 minutes till 9.
Can you go any faster?
Not unless you want the full attention
of the world press.
There was no consensus
after the first ballot...
...but Cardinal Baggia, the Italian,
is the odds-on favorite....
There is no new Pope,
but it is possible...
...that Cardinal Guidera, the Spaniard,
is the most probable....
It is possible that Cardinal Ebner,
from Germany, is the favorite....
Stem cell research is murder!
You're condemning sick people to die.
Man is not God.
There, another obelisk.
Check the crowd. It's almost 9.
He's gotta be here already.
There must be 100 statues
up there.
None of them are angels.
Those are all saints.
How in God's name would anyone
create a sculpture about air?
Bas-relief. Of course.
It's still a sculpture.
Check the ground.
Look at the carvings.
Look for another having something
to do with air.
"West Ponente." West wind.
Vittoria!
Here it is.
West wind. An angel
blowing out five streaks of air.
This is it.
Get the police!
Call an ambulance!
He's still alive.
His chest.
They punctured his lungs.
Clear the square.
"--from within your walls to squeeze
life from the Bishop."
He's actually claiming responsibility
for the death of His Holiness.
That's ridiculous.
He died of a stroke.
It implies the Illuminati murdered him
with his own medication.
What?
Down here.
"With man's solution
we stilled his heart.
With his own needle
did we pierce his unholy veil."
Did the Holy Father take any kind
of medication by injection?
Tinzaparin.
He had thrombophlebitis.
He took an injection every day.
But no one knew that.
Someone knew.
Well, he had health concerns
and seizures as well.
But he took steps to make sure
he was watched, for safety.
He didn't want it made public,
so we have no reason to discuss it.
Tinzaparin is lethal
in the wrong dosage.
An overdose could cause
massive internal bleeding...
...and brain hemorrhages.
It might look like a stroke at first, but in
a few days his body would show signs.
This could easily be examined.
In case you're not aware of it...
...papal autopsy is prohibited
by Vatican law.
We're not going to defile
His Holiness's body...
...just because his enemies claim--
-Why would they send this letter now?
-Well, to cause panic.
"The sun will blind at midnight...
...and neither police nor professors
can stop it."
He knows I'm here.
Obviously they were hoping
this letter would become public.
We might be wise to preempt
their attempt...
...by making an announcement
of our own to refute this absurd claim.
That's out of the question.
Cardinal Strauss has insisted
this entire matter be kept internal.
He shouldn't be aware of it.
He's in conclave.
His final instructions before sealing
the doors were very clear.
Cardinal Strauss does not dictate
Vatican protocols.
As you say, yet, technically...
...now that conclave has begun...
...it's his privilege and duty
to control public announcements.
I've drafted a release
about the incident in the piazza...
...but any other statements
are specifically prohibited.
For that, Cardinal has asked me
to remind you we have a chimney.
Commander Richter,
the search for the device?
Well, we've turned the power on and
off to about 20 percent of Vatican City.
-Nothing on the video yet.
-We're running out of options.
How long would you need
to evacuate?
If I pull all my men from the search
for the bomb, 30 minutes.
Mr. Langdon. You have been right
so far about the path. It's now 9:15.
How quickly can you find
the next church?
The lines on the carving pointed east,
away from Vatican City.
But there were five of them,
so there's room for error.
About 20 churches intersect
those lines.
None of them have names
that invoke fire.
So a Bernini sculpture must be inside
one of them that does.
We'll need to get
into the archives to find it.
-Would you escort Mr. Langdon?
-Yes, Father.
Silvano's journals.
The killer's name could be in here.
May I stay?
Please. Fine, of course.
Professor.
Would it surprise you to find
those clothes suit you?
It would surprise the hell out of me.
The Vatican is expressing sympathy
for the mugging victim...
...a Düsseldorf tourist,
now confirmed dead....
The Vatican police have a suspect
in custody....
The Vatican will allow the crowd back
into St. Peter's Square...
...where security will be doubled....
The Vatican did admit that where there
are crowds, so often follows crime.
We're trying now to get the name
of the tourist who was--
-Oh, wait.
-Hand to the right. Keep panning.
We're getting word now of smoke.
Smoke from
the Sistine Chapel chimney.
Apparently there's been
another vote.
The smoke is black.
Once again, the cardinals have failed
to reach consensus...
...and the Catholic Church
remains without a leader.
What are you looking for now?
Church assets.
I beg your pardon?
Artwork. It's valuable.
Corporations tend to keep track
of their holdings.
The Catholic Church
is not a corporation, it's a beacon.
A source of inspiration for one billion
lost and frightened souls.
Sure, I get that. It's also a bank.
Commander Olivetti said I was not
to leave your side this time.
It wasn't me, it was her.
Power is now cut to Zone 73.
No light reaction on the monitor.
Restore power and move on to 74.
What sort of signs?
I'm sorry?
If the Holy Father was given
an overdose of Tinzaparin...
...what signs would his body bear?
Bleeding of the oral mucosa.
His tongue.
Postmortem, the blood congeals and
turns the inside of the mouth black.
Even after 14 days?
It wouldn't show up
until at least a week after his death.
He was very important to me.
Yeah, I understand.
Will you come with me, please?
Signore, would you organize
a security team...
...to escort Miss Vetra and myself
down to the crypt?
-Yes, sir.
-We'll be leaving straightaway.
Do you smoke?
A little bit.
Then you better sit down
before you keel over.
And what's all that right there?
What does this say
in Italian right here...
...next to the Ecstasy of Saint Teresa?
Right there.
"Moved at suggestion of the artist."
"Moved"? To another church.
At the suggestion of Bernini?
I don't know.
Here. Translate all of this for me...
...and I'll buy you a pack of smokes.
I'm looking for a reference to fire.
Fires.
-"Seraphim," meaning "the fiery one."
-Right.
"His great, golden spear,
a point of fire."
Then "woman left completely afire."
Ecstasy of Saint Teresa.
Saint Teresa on fire.
So this sculpture
was moved to this church?
Why did they shut down the system?
They know we're down here.
If there's no power,
there's no oxygen.
-Can we get out?
-The door is electronic.
Oh, God.
Well, that's disappointing.
Where are we going?
To see my father.
I don't understand.
I was orphaned when I was 9 years
of age. A bombing in Ulster.
The UVF protesting the visit
of a Catholic archbishop.
The archbishop felt responsible,
and he adopted me the following day.
I was raised by him
and by the Church.
He was the wisest man I ever met.
Even when I was young and stubborn,
I wanted to be ordained.
But I was brought up in Italy, so l
also wanted to do my military service.
I wanted to fight.
He told me, "Learn to fly."
So I joined
the Aeronautica Militare...
...flew helicopters,
bringing the wounded back to hospital.
He was a great man.
Your father died?
Fourteen days ago.
Command, do you read me?
Power is off. Oxygen is very low.
Come in. Can you read me?
Can you get anything?
No. The walls are lead-lined.
There's no signal.
This way.
If the Holy Father was murdered,
the implications are profound.
Vatican security is impenetrable.
No one from the outside
could have got anywhere near him.
It was someone on the inside.
And we can trust no one.
No light reaction on Zone 97.
Based on the rate the battery
is using power...
...the device will detonate
just before midnight.
Holy Father...
...when I was young, you told me
the voice in my heart was God's voice.
You said I should follow it,
no matter how painful.
Forgive me.
Please.
Give me strength.
What I do, I do in the name
of everything you believe.
Remove the cover.
Did you not hear me?
Signore, by law,
we are at you command, but--
One day I will ask your forgiveness for
putting you in this position.
But today I ask your obedience.
Vatican laws are there
to protect this church.
And it's in that spirit that I command
you to break one of them now.
God help us.
Santa Maria della Vittoria.
Do you know it?
-Yes, I do.
-It's the next church.
I think someone just tried to kill me.
-l promise you we had no idea--
-He knows I'm here.
-Yes.
-You heard me ask permission.
-You gave me an escort.
-We had no idea...
...that portions of our white zones
were cross-wired with that building.
Commander Richter
was extending the search.
If he had known,
he never would have killed the power.
Or there is the other possibility.
Is it conceivable the Illuminati...
...have infiltrated the Swiss Guard?
Perhaps.
-l wanna speak to the camerlengo.
-The camerlengo is unavailable.
He's found evidence that the
Holy Father was indeed murdered.
-He is seeking guidance.
-From whom?
From God.
-Make an effort. Please.
-Yeah, yeah.
The journals. Where are they?
Who took the journals
from this desk?
Someone is here? What is this?
Signore, this is unacceptable.
For a camerlengo to enter the chapel
once conclave has begun....
Forgive me.
There's been a development.
His Holiness Celestine V
was murdered.
Is it so hard to believe
it could happen again?
Signori, please a moment.
Please, signori.
Our Church is at war.
We are under attack
from an old enemy.
The Illuminati.
They have struck us from within.
Murdering our Holy Father.
And threatening us all with destruction
at the hands of their new god, science.
They call it retribution.
They think it justified.
Because of the Church's attacks
on men of science in the past.
And it's true.
Since the days of Galileo...
...this Church has tried to slow
the relentless march of progress...
...sometimes with misguided means.
But science and religion
are not enemies.
There are simply some things...
...that science is just too young
to understand.
So the Church pleads,
"Stop. Slow down. Think. Wait."
And for this they call us backward.
But who is more ignorant...
...the man
who cannot define lightning...
...or the man who does not respect
its natural awesome power?
The battle is well underway, signori.
We must defend ourselves.
But what if this time we fight
their stealth with openness?
Combat their wicked scheme
with simple truth...
...and end this brutish battle
once and for all.
We must open the doors, tear down the
blacken curtains and speak to our flock.
If the outside world could see
this Church as I do...
...looking beyond the ritual
of these walls...
...they would see a modern miracle.
A brotherhood of imperfect,
simple souls...
...who want nothing more
than to be voices of compassion...
...in a world spinning out of control.
Signori, I ask...
...l pray...
...that you break this conclave.
Open the doors...
...evacuate St. Peter's Square...
...and tell the world the truth.
Oh, my God.
Get him down!
No!
There, there, that chain.
On that pulley.
This bench. Get this pew up here.
Make a ladder.
My son...
...God answers all prayers...
...but sometimes his answer is no.
The College will not break conclave.
May I suggest...
...you direct your energies...
...to helping the Swiss Guard find
this explosive device...
...if it exists.
And leave Church leadership...
...to its leaders.
Eminence.
There is a growing fear
that without the four prefefiti...
...a two-thirds majority
for any candidate will not be possible.
-Unless--
-Speak plainly.
It is the recommendation of many...
...that you ask to be removed
from your post as Great Elector...
...thereby making yourself eligible...
...to wear the Ring of the Fisherman.
Well...
...if it is God's will...
...may his will be done.
Signore, are you okay?
Those journals are private property.
I demand you return them.
They're material evidence
in a Vatican investigation.
I am an Italian citizen.
My rights do not end...
-...just because I crossed to the other--
-This is not Italy.
It's not even Rome, it's the Vatican.
A country of its own
with its own laws.
And when those journals passed
the border, they became my property.
I will give them back to you...
...when I've decided they contain
nothing of value to the investigation.
Do you have something to hide,
Comandante Richter?
Do you, Dr. Vetra?
Were it up to me,
it would not be this way.
It's a sin to kill with pain.
It's a sin to kill without reason.
Father...
...they make me a sinner.
Saint Teresa on fire.
Professor Langdon?
-What direction is that?
-West, I think.
"'Cross Rome
the mystic elements unfold."
Piazza Barberini is here.
Saint Teresa is here.
Where is the Santa Maria
del Popolo?
-Santa Maria del Popolo?
-Yes.
Thank you.
St. Peter's is here.
We are here.
A church with water....
Wait, wait, wait.
"'Cross Rome."
The poem must mean it literally,
cross Rome.
Professor, Commander Richter
has ordered me...
...to escort you to the Vatican.
Piazza Navona.
Earth. Air. Fire. Water.
Cross Rome.
Bernini's Four Rivers.
Professor Langdon, the Vatican insists
that I have to take you back.
The Vatican is about to see
its fourth cardinal murdered tonight.
Now, look. You can do as they say
and force me back to the Vatican...
...where we can all mourn
his death together.
Or you can show how real cops act,
and take me to the Piazza Navona...
...where we still might be able
to stop it.
Oh, by all means, let's talk it over.
In 14 minutes, he's gonna be dead.
This way, professor.
Yes, Padre?
At 11:15,
if the Church is still in peril...
...give the order
to evacuate the cardinals.
But with dignity.
Let them walk out into St. Peter's
Square with their heads held high.
I don't want the last image
of this Church to be of men...
...sneaking out the back door.
"Let angels guide thee...."
There it is.
-There it is.
-Professor, I know this fountain.
-There is no angel on it.
-The dove. The Angel of Peace.
And it's looking in what direction?
East, I think.
Professor, just wait here.
Stay put.
Good evening. Can you help me?
I'm waiting for a doctor.
Come here.
Stay calm. Don't shoot.
Hey!
Help!
Somebody help!
Help, somebody!
Cardinal Baggia?
Cardinal Baggia.
Where was he hiding you?
The Church of Illumination,
where is it?
Castel-- Castel Sant'Angelo.
Castle of the Angel.
Sir, there's news
about Cardinal Baggia.
The cardinal told Langdon he was
being held in Castel Sant'Angelo.
If Langdon's right,
that's where the bomb is.
Send everyone we can spare.
And you?
I'm staying here.
Vittoria.
-You're all right.
-I'm all right.
What about you? I just heard.
I'm all right, I'm okay.
Robert, we can't trust Richter.
He took Silvano's journals.
There must be something in there
he doesn't want us to see.
The head of the Swiss Guard.
Castel Sant'Angelo, it's close,
so the signal from that camera...
...could still reach the Vatican.
The Church of Illumination
is somewhere here.
Your canister is inside it.
Come with me.
For 400 years, the Illuminati
met right under the Church's nose.
The Vatican used this as a hideout
and as a prison for their enemies.
If the explosion happens here, would
the blast radius take out the Vatican?
And part of Rome along with it.
Go on.
They're pointing to it. The angels.
The canister must be down there.
Come on.
-Where are they going?
-To search the outer castle.
No, no. It has to be here!
Robert, it's a dead end.
No, it's not.
See if you can find a flashlight.
All of these stones
are rectangular granite.
Except right here. What is this?
It's a pentagram.
An eye...
...that leads to....
Nowhere.
Robert?
These walls overlap
and there's a passageway back here.
Here, let me have the flashlight.
It's a passageway
that leads to the Vatican.
An ancient escape route.
My God.
Here.
Look.
This would be the perfect place
for the Illuminati to blow...
...the whole building up.
Here. Here.
Get on the radio. Get the word out.
Conclave remains sealed.
But the camerlengo gave the order
for evacuation at--
I'm countermanding it.
This is it. This is their church.
The canister should be lit
by artificial light.
It's not here, Robert.
"A shining star at the end of the path."
It has to be.
It's not here.
-What did the poem say?
-Nothing.
Nothing, it's all over. It was just the
four lines, each one describing the....
There's a fifth brand.
It's not an ambigram,
it's just two crossed keys.
-The symbol for the Vatican.
-No.
No, the papacy.
They intend to kill him.
Before they destroy the Vatican,
they're gonna kill...
-...and brand the pope himself.
-There is no pope.
Tempe sede vacante.
ll camerlengo.
-We have to warn him.
-Take a step back, please.
Take your cell phone
from your pocket.
Throw it in the fire.
Murderer.
You know, when they call me...
...and they all call me...
...it is so important to them
that I know...
...that what they ask
is the Lord's will.
Or Allah's, or Yahweh's.
And I suppose they're right.
Because if he was not vengeful,
I would not exist, now would I?
I've had several chances
to eliminate you tonight.
You're still alive
because you have no weapon...
...and they didn't ask me to kill you,
but if you pursue me...
...it is another matter.
Be careful.
These are men of God.
The camerlengo.
-Camerlengo will grant you audience.
-Good.
I'd like to see him alone.
That's impossible, sir.
No one sees the camerlengo alone.
Have you forgotten
who you're working for?
No, sir.
Have you come to make me a martyr?
Here. Here. Here.
-l need to see the camerlengo.
-He is not available.
-l demand to see the camerlengo!
We'll see about that.
All locked up. Senza chiave,
it's a one-way portal.
The only entrance
is on the other side.
No! Hey!
I don't care who he talks to.
He doesn't go into that room.
This is Robert Langdon and Dr. Vetra!
Open the door!
Open up!
Hey!
The camerlengo is in danger.
He's the one! He's got a gun!
-Illuminatus!
-You bastard.
-Sanctimonious bastard!
Order the evacuation.
We only have 19 minutes.
Here, he's--
Get the helicopter
for the older cardinals.
Yes, sir.
Robert?
The brand, the symbol,
could it have another meaning?
Crossed keys.
But those are upside down.
St. Peter.
The first pope...
...was crucified upside down.
-On Vatican Hill.
-A few hundred feet below us.
Necropolis, city of the dead.
"Upon this rock
I will build my church."
Or bring it down upon itself.
The bomb is in St. Peter's tomb.
The grid is still cycling.
The power to this section
must be down.
It must be here. It must be.
Don't touch it.
We have seven minutes.
Robert, hold this.
It's cold down here, isn't it?
What's wrong?
Cold decreases battery life.
We may have less than five minutes.
So?
If I pull the power
with less than five minutes...
...the residual charge
won't hold suspension.
We should leave it here
and get clear if we can.
-At least down here, the damage--
-No!
-No, wait!
-Father!
We are live here
at St. Peter's Square...
...where despite a bomb threat
and an order of evacuation...
...the crowd is actually growing
in size as we await an official...
...announcement
from the Vatican spokesman...
...as to the exact nature
of the threat...
...and whether or not they
are treating it as a credible danger.
This way.
A bomb?
Roberto, there's an emergency.
I'll take her up alone.
He's got clearance.
Oh, my God.
Get down!
Cardinal Strauss?
It was the camerlengo.
He saved us all!
He saved the church and he is alive.
Praise God. Praise God.
He is alive.
He sacrificed himself for all of us.
It's so incredible. He survived.
You know, the worst thing
we thought would happen...
...was that our work would fall into
the hands of the energy companies.
We thought
we could change the world.
So naive.
No, no. Not naive.
Innocent, maybe.
But that's not a crime.
I'm not so sure.
Go back to work.
Change the world.
A gift. Do you understand
what I'm saying?
For Catholics, for everyone.
Camerlengo's age
shouldn't be an obstacle.
Signori, you are no doubt aware...
...that by holy law the man is ineligible
for election to the papacy.
He is not a cardinal, he is a priest.
He is of insufficient age.
Well, maybe there's a way
we could consider the possibilities.
I am sorry. The protocols of conclave
are not subject to modification.
I will not call a ballot on this matter.
But, signore,
you would not call the ballot.
Surely you remember...
...you gave up your post
as Great Elector.
They are singing
in St. Peter's Square.
And what happened here tonight
transcends our laws.
Does it?
Is it God's will
that we give ourselves over to frenzy?
Discard the rules of the Church?
Perhaps we need not discard them.
Signore, I am thinking now of Romano
Pontifici Eligendo, Numero Sessanta--
Acclamation by Adoration.
If the Holy Spirit speaks
through us...
...and we call a man's name
out loud--
That is election by adoration.
-He's God's choice.
-Yes.
And the candidate need only be
an ordained member of the clergy...
...present in the Sistine Chapel
at the moment of his election.
I think we have it settled.
Signore Camerlengo.
Yes?
The cardinals ask you to join them
in conclave as soon as possible.
Me?
Yes, Padre.
What are you doing?
Silvano's journals. I want them back.
Richter said...
...His Holiness suffered
from seizures...
...but steps were taken...
...for safety.
"Made sure he was watched,"
he said.
What if he was trying
to give me this key?
That's the papal office.
If the pope was worried
about seizures...
...he must have had Richter
install cameras without telling anyone.
To keep an eye on him. For safety.
Maybe it records.
I read the journals, Patrick.
The scientist kept journals. So?
Well, you figure prominently
in them.
Really?
Bentivoglio wasn't just a physicist,
he was also a Catholic priest.
And as such, he was deeply conflicted
about the implications of his work...
...and in need of spiritual guidance.
Like Galileo.
About a month ago, he requested
an audience with the pope...
...but you know that.
Because you granted the audience,
and you were also present during it.
The God particle.
To actually claim an act of creation.
The blasphemy. The arrogance.
The Holy Father didn't see it
like that.
He urged him to go public.
His Holiness
thought that the discovery...
...could actually scientifically prove
the existence of a divine power...
...and begin to bridge the gap
between science and religion.
His work was not religious,
it was sacrilegious.
But you saw the pope's position
as a softening of Church law.
As an old man's weakness.
Your father's weakness.
You murdered the Vicar of Christ.
He raised me to protect this Church,
even from within.
And then you conjured up
an old enemy from the past.
The Illuminati.
You found the ancient brands in the
papal vaults, and put them to use.
To spread fear.
The cardinals are men of belief.
Right now, their belief in evil
is uniting them.
The entire Catholic world
will be united by this attack.
There is no attack.
You're trying to convince the cardinals
they're in a war...
...so they will choose a warrior
to lead them.
We are at war.
We're weak
when we should be strong.
If science is allowed
to claim the power of creation...
...what is left for God?
It didn't work, Patrick.
-It isn't finished.
-Oh, yes, it's finished.
It's finished.
I've shown the journals
to Father Simeon.
The moment the doors
to the conclave open...
...he will tell the cardinals
what you've done.
I was planning on doing this alone.
Put it down.
But perhaps it's better
that you're here.
Put it down.
Put it away.
Help! He's the one! He's got a gun!
-Illuminatus!
-You bastard.
-Sanctimonious bastard!
And get the helicopter
for the older cardinals, right?
Robert?
The brand, the symbol,
could it have another meaning?
I've been summoned by
the College of Cardinals.
Gently...
...but within our walls.
Father, into thy hands
I commend my spirit.
Church sources now confirm...
...that Camerlengo
Father Patrick McKenna...
...has died of internal injuries
sustained in his heroic fall.
Crowds of the faithful are calling for...
...the camerlengo's immediate
canonization and sainthood.
The Vatican also announced
the death of three of its cardinals...
...in the fire
at Santa Maria della Vittoria.
--as we await the appearance
of the new Holy Father...
...Cardinal Baggia of Italy...
...one of the four original prefefiti,
who, despite terrorist attempts...
...at disruption,
seems to have been selected...
...in one of the swiftest
and smoothest conclaves...
...in modern Church history.
Professor Langdon? Please.
A token of thanks
from His Holiness...
...and from his new camerlengo.
We are grateful you saved his life.
And it's our understanding
that you require this text...
...to complete your scholarly work.
We ask only that
in your last will and testament...
...you ensure...
...it finds its way home.
Of course.
And when you write of us...
...and you will write of us...
...may I ask one thing?
Do so gently.
I'll try.
Religion is flawed...
...but only because man is flawed.
All men, including this one.
He chose the name Luke.
There's been many Marks
and Johns...
...never a Luke.
It's said he was a doctor.
It's quite a message,
science and faith all in one.
The world is in need of both.
You will counsel him wisely.
I am an old man.
I will counsel him briefly.
Mr. Langdon...
...thanks be to God for sending
someone to protect his Church.
I don't believe he sent me, Father.
Oh, my son...
...of course he did.